Guide to the Ruth Jespersen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ruth Jespersen papers
1976-1990
YCAL MSS 708
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.42
(5 boxes)
The Ruth Jespersen Papers consist of correspondence, writings, audiocassettes, and printed material regarding the professional life of the American writer Ruth Jespersen. Correspondence includes letters between Jespersen and Stephen Baily and Steven Milhauser and a letter from Jespersen to Phil Lyman. Writings contain typescript drafts, typescript photocopies, printed versions, and photocopies of printed versions of Jespersen's poetry, prose, a teleplay, and a screenplay. Two audiocassettes contain Jespersen reading The Blink of an Eye, a screenplay written by Jespersen and Michael O'Rourke. Printed material includes printed versions of Jespersen's publications and photocopies of publicity.
Jespersen, Ruth
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ruth Jespersen, 1993-1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Ruth Jespersen
Ruth Jespersen, American poet, and prose, teleplay, and screenplay writer.
Scope and Contents
The Ruth Jespersen Papers consist of correspondence, writings, audiocassettes, and printed material regarding the professional life of the American writer. Correspondence includes letters between Jespersen and Stephen Baily and Steven Milhauser and a letter from Jespersen to Phil Lyman. Writings contain typescript drafts, typescript photocopies, printed versions, and photocopies of printed versions of Jespersen's poetry, prose, a teleplay, and a screenplay. Two audiocassettes contain Jespersen reading The Blink of an Eye, a screenplay written by Jespersen and Michael O'Rourke. Printed material includes printed versions of Jespersen's publications and photocopies of publicity.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: I. December 1993 Acquisition, 1976-1989. II. February 1995 Acquisition, 1990. III. July 1996 Acquisition, undated.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials; Scripts; Sound recordings; Television scripts; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Baily, Stephen; Jespersen, Ruth; Lyman, Phil; Milhauser, Steven; O'Rourke, Michael
- December 1993 Acquisition, 1976-1989, undated; 1; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 307
  - Correspondence between Stephen Baily and Steven Milhauser, with index, 1976-1988; 6 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Phil Lyman at the Gotham Book Mart regarding a contribution to the Francis Steloff Memorial Lecture at Skidmore College, 1989 April 23 (Box 1)
  - Typescript drafts (photocopies) of poems and bibliography, undated (Box 1)
  - Typescript drafts (photocopies) and printed versions of poems and other writings published between 1954 and 1988, undated; 46 (Box 1)
  - The Strange Ordeal of Edwin Panquo (Biblia Candida, 1979) (Box 1)
  - The Printer's Devil, Volume I, Number 2, 1986 November 22 (Box 1)
- February 1995 Acquisition, 1990, undated; 2; 0.42; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 427
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 2 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - The Blink of an Eye, written with Michael O'Rourke, screenplay, typescript, with two audiocassettes of Jespersen reading from The Blink of an Eye, 1990; 3 (Box 2)
    - Ruth Jespersen reading The Blink of an Eye, 1990; 1; 01:02:10; There is static on the tape. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002091396946)
      The recording references the date as July 24, 1983.
    - Ruth Jespersen reading The Blink of an Eye, 1990; 1; 01:02:09; There is a warble in the audio about halfway through the recording. (Box 2, Item barcode 39002091396953)
  - "High Dudgeon", written with Michael O'Rourke, teleplay, typescript, undated (Box 2)
  - Photocopies of newspaper columns by Jespersen, 1990-1993, undated; 3 (Box 2)
- July 1996 Acquisition, undated; 3; (3 boxes)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 490
  Writings, typescript, various drafts. Includes novellas, plays, poetry and short stories. Titles include A Different Girl; Death and Windows; Helen, or The True Beginnings of our End; In Populous City Pent; and Testament.
  - Photocopy of orange ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - Bibliographies (Box 3)
    - A Piece of Scholarship (Box 3)
    - Blue Nun (Box 3)
    - A Memoir (Box 3)
    - Happy Daze (Box 3)
    - When Day is Done (Box 3)
    - Stairs (Box 3)
    - Pop (Box 3)
    - Harry's Exceptional Kindness (Box 3)
    - Epitaph (Box 3)
    - After the War (Box 3)
    - Yport (Box 3)
    - The Buchsbaum Papers (Box 3)
    - A Well-Earned Rebuff (Box 3)
    - A Composition (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of black ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - Helen, or The True Beginning of Our End (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of red ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - In Populous City Pent p. 1-45 (Box 3)
    - In Populous City Pent p. 46-100 (Box 3)
    - In Populous City Pent p. 101-151 (Box 3)
    - In Populous City Pent p. 152-205 (Box 3)
    - In Populous City Pent p. 206-244 (Box 3)
    - In Populous City Pent p. 245-308 (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of red ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - Testament Chapters 1-4 (Box 3)
    - Testament Chapters 5-7 (Box 3)
    - Testament Chapters 8-10 (Box 3)
    - Testament Chapters 11-15 (Box 3)
    - Testament Chapters 16-Epilogue (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of green ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - A Name to Conjure With (Box 3)
    - Dora in Her Own Defense (Box 3)
    - The Yellow Silk Scarf (Box 3)
    - The Lifeguard (Box 3)
    - Semi-Private (Box 3)
    - Please Answer Soon (Box 3)
    - Pictures at an Exhibition (Box 3)
    - The Education of Martin (Box 3)
    - He (Box 3)
    - The Song of the Dress (Box 3)
    - Field Day (Box 3)
    - Grandchild (Box 3)
    - No Strings Attached (Box 3)
    - Epitaph (Box 3)
    - Shaggy Eyedrops (Box 3)
    - Chez Hernandez (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of green ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - Larry Kramer, Esq. Waxes Fat (Box 3)
    - The Petition (Box 3)
    - Sybil (Box 3)
    - Escaping Miss Finch (Box 3)
    - Charlaque (Box 3)
    - Good Old Days in the Village (Box 3)
    - Bimbo (Box 3)
    - The Portrait of Mr. Bohak (Box 3)
    - Bonanza (Box 3)
    - What's a Man to Do? (Box 3)
    - A Shot of Brandy (Box 3)
    - The World of Marmaduke Chambers (Box 3)
    - Loretta Ann Burbage Speaks Her Mind (Box 3)
    - Mr. Hazeltine (Box 3)
    - Three Years Down and Eighty to Go (Box 3)
    - True Love Doth Pass Away (Box 3)
    - We Spell Amusement with a Capital A (Box 3)
    - Brunhilde: or Human Hate (Box 3)
    - The Cellini Incident (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of olive green ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - A Father's Love (Box 3)
    - Fair is Fair (Box 3)
    - The Twelve Days of Christmas (Box 3)
    - Folk Wisdom (Box 3)
    - Sybil (Box 3)
    - I, Siddhartha (Box 3)
    - In Memoriam Joe Singer (1950-1993) (Box 3)
    - Hymn to the Status Quo (Box 3)
    - Yport (Box 3)
    - Another Psychologist Named Lawrence (Box 3)
    - Winifred (Box 3)
    - A Likely Story (Box 3)
    - Here Comes Norah (Box 3)
    - Reba at Home (Box 3)
    - Constantine's Misfortune (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of black ring binder the following material was in (Box 4)
    - Subterranean Nightlife and Literary Scene (Box 4)
    - My Dinner with Grishkin (Box 4)
    - The Magic Marker (Box 4)
    - From the Library (Box 4)
    - Hymn to the Status Quo (Box 4)
    - A Smashing Exit (Box 4)
    - The Bird of Dawning (Box 4)
    - The Enigma Variations (Box 4)
    - Out of Thine Own Mouth (Box 4)
    - The Doctor Sproggins Company (Box 4)
    - Humanity At Bay (Box 4)
    - Family (Box 4)
    - Tea and Comfortable Advice (Box 4)
    - Buffcolored Birches and a Tearose Sky (Box 4)
    - Out of Line (Box 4)
    - Walter's Letter (Box 4)
    - A Quiet Sunday (title page only) (Box 4)
    - The Petition (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of dark green ring binder the following material was in (Box 4)
    - Abominations (Box 4)
    - Benevolence (Box 4)
    - A Piano Piece (Box 4)
    - An Evening with Arlene Ardath (Box 4)
    - Death of a Dog (Box 4)
    - The Sleepwriter (Box 4)
    - A Likely Story (Box 4)
    - Disobedience (Box 4)
    - The Girl Most Likely to Succeed (Box 4)
    - Family (Box 4)
    - A Multitude of Souls (Box 4)
    - How Dare You (Box 4)
    - Eidolon (Box 4)
    - We're Going to the Country Now (Box 4)
    - Mr. Loomis Makes an Offer (Box 4)
    - The Healer (Box 4)
    - The Baron (Box 4)
    - The Musing in the Window (Box 4)
    - Grishkin on the Phone (Box 4)
    - Uncle Wembley's Book Party (Box 4)
    - The Two Kinds of Writing (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of white ring binder the following material was in (Box 4)
    - Pop (Box 4)
    - Constantine's Misfortune (Box 4)
    - Play in novel In Populous City Pent (Box 4)
    - Benevolence (Box 4)
    - Sandwiched (Box 4)
    - The Brigham Brittons, 2 (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of red ring binder the following material was in (Box 4)
    - Gautier, 2 (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of brown ring binder the following material was in (Box 4)
    - Dora in Her Own Defense (Box 4)
    - The King and the Professor (Box 4)
    - The Sketchbook of Americana Orville (Box 4)
    - The Strange Ordeal of Edwin Banquo (Box 4)
    - The False Step of Annalise (Box 4)
    - The Cough (Box 4)
    - Mildred (Box 4)
    - The Supervisor (Box 4)
    - Fontainebleu (Box 4)
    - Grandchild (Box 4)
    - Rhapsody in Balneal Rock (Box 4)
    - Innocentia in Terra Mirabili (Box 4)
    - At Mrs. Suwalki's (Box 4)
    - The Timidity of Luriana Lurilee (Box 4)
    - Fled Is That Music (Box 4)
    - The Plant (Box 4)
    - Beastliness at Beauvais (Box 4)
    - Ils Ont Visite les Pays-Bas, Ils Rentrent a Terre Haute (Box 4)
    - Innocenza Abroad Years Later (Box 4)
    - In Mountainbrim Hospital (Box 4)
    - Poetry and Verse, 2 (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of navy ring binder (Box 4)
  - Photocopy of white ring binder the following material was in (Box 3)
    - A Chapter from Testament (Box 5)
    - Pearl Button's Birthday Party (Box 5)
    - As it says in Job: How forcible are right words! (Box 5)
    - All Be as Before, Love (Box 5)
    - The Double (Box 5)
    - Apartment House, or What You Will (Box 5)
    - Nellie (Box 5)
    - Report of Mr. Glubb of the Bureau of Child Welfare (Box 5)
    - The Robber Baroness (Box 5)
    - Asterisk Politics: An Incendiary Tale (Box 5)
    - Bonnie (Box 5)
    - The Inkhornist (Box 5)
  - Photocopy of white ring binder the following material was in (Box 5)
    - Speranza (Box 5)
    - Sandwiched (Box 5)
    - Heart Attack (Box 5)
    - Epitaph (Box 5)
    - De Gustibus (Box 5)
    - Murder (Box 5)
    - The Witzig Tale (Box 5)
    - Head of a Woman (Box 5)
    - High Dudgeon (Box 5)
    - The Anatomy of Human Destructiveness (Box 5)
    - Madder Music and Stronger Wine (Box 5)
    - A Joke (Box 5)
    - Delilah Retires (Box 5)
    - Twelfth Night (Box 5)
    - From A to Z: Angelo and Zinaida (Box 5)
    - No Strings Attached (Box 5)
    - The Holy Grail (Box 5)
    - About the Dedication Page (Box 5)
  - Photocopy of blue denim ring binder the following material was in (Box 5)
    - High Dudgeon (Box 5)
    - Observances, Profane and Sacred (Box 5)
    - Innocenza Abroad (Box 5)
    - Bertie Brought to the Test (Box 5)
    - The Happy Farmer (Box 5)
    - Two Girls: A Chromatic Fantasy (Box 5)
    - Isabel for the Time Being (Box 5)
  - Photocopy of white ring binder the following material was in (Box 5)
    - Natasha (Box 5)
    - Whatever Happened to Our Flower (Box 5)
    - Children? (Box 5)
    - Beneath the Moon (Box 5)
    - Whim, Lose or Draw (Box 5)
    - We Must Cultivate Our Garden (Box 5)
    - Once, Twice, Three Times a Lady (Box 5)
    - At O'Houlihan's (Box 5)
    - Some Journal Entries (Box 5)
    - A Love Affair (Box 5)
    - Coffee at Nedick's (Box 5)
    - A Serious Disquisition on a Terribly Funny Subject (Box 5)
    - The Mask (Box 5)
    - Self-Portrait (Box 5)
    - Me and Show Biz (Box 5)
    - Confessions of a Dumb Blonde (Box 5)
    - Happy Daze (Box 5)
    - The Look (Box 5)
    - We Must Speak by the Card, or Equivocation Will Undo Us (Box 5)
    - A Job with a Reputable Firm (Box 5)
    - Threnody for Little Old Ladies (Box 5)
  - Photocopy of blue denim ring binder the following material was in (Box 5)
    - A Quiet Sunday (Box 5)
    - At the Dunes (Box 5)
    - Send Me a Person for Myself (Box 5)
    - Never Seek to Tell Thy Love (Box 5)
    - Hold Not My Western Heritage Against Me (Box 5)
    - Gilliam Clicks (Box 5)
    - When Lovely Woman Stoops to Folly (Box 5)
    - Desperately Seeking Antonia (Box 5)
    - Turnabout is Fair Play (Box 5)
    - Parn Me (Box 5)
    - Reparation (Box 5)
    - One of the poems from Gautier in prose form (Box 5)
    - Heaven Can Wait (Box 5)
    - Ariel Beset (Box 5)
    - Flying the Coop (Box 5)
    - The Holy Grail (Box 5)
    - How Did Youse Guys Know Us Broads Was Collitch Goils (Box 5)
    - Departure (Box 5)
    - Thirty Years Later (Box 5)
    - Some Notes from My First Year of Widowhood (Box 5)
  - Photocopy of blue ring binder the following material was in (Box 5)
    - Death and Windows (Box 5)
    - A Different Girl, with Memorial Day (a novel by Frederick Dexter Berlin) (Box 5)